天香字幕社
t x s u b
Hey...
ねえ
They say it's five centimeters per second.
秒速5センチなんだって
えっ　何？
Huh? What is?
桜の花の落ちるスピード 秒速5センチメートル
The speed at which cherry blossoms fall.
It's five centimeters per second.
ふうん
You sure know a lot of stuff like that, Akari.
アカリ　そういうこと
よく知ってるよね
ふふん
Say... don't you think it kinda looks like snow?
ねえ　なんだか　まるで
雪みたいじゃない？
I guess...
すうかなー
あっ
ハァ　ハァ
Hey! Wait up!
ねえ！
待ってよ！
アカリ！
Akari!
Takaki-kun!
タカキくん
来年も一緒に桜　見れるといいね！
It'd be great if we could watch the cherry
blossoms fall again together next year.
遠野タカキさまへ　たいへんご無沙汰しております
"To Thono Takaki-sama. "
"It's been a really long time. "
こちらの夏も暑いけれど
"Summer's pretty hot around here,
but compared to Tokyo, it's so much milder. "
東京に比べれば　ずっと過ごしやすいです
でも今にして思えば
私は東京のあのムシ暑い夏も好きでした
"But when I think about it,
I liked Tokyo's hot, humid summers, too. "
溶けてしまいそうに熱いアスファルトも
陽炎のむこうの高層ビルも
"The melting-hot asphalt,"
"the distant skyscrapers, shimmering in the heat,"
"and the freezing air-conditioning
in department stores and on subways. "
デパートや地下鉄の寒いくらいの冷房も
"The last time we were together was at
our elementary school graduation. "
私たちが最後に会ったのは
小学校の卒業式でしたから
"It's already been half a year since. "
あれからもう半年です
"So, Takaki-kun... "
ねえ　タカキくん
"... do you still remember me?."
私のこと　覚えていますか？
前略　タカキくんへ
"Dear Takaki-kun... "
お返事ありがとう　嬉しかったです
"Thanks for replying. "
"It made me so happy. "
もうすっかり秋ですね
こちらは紅葉がキレイです
"It's already well into autumn and the
leaves are turning beautiful colors. "
"I had to pull out a sweater the day before
yesterday for the first time this year. "
今年　最初のセーターをおととい私は出しました
遠野くん!
Tohno-kun.
Senpai.
先輩
何？アブレター？
What's that? A love letter?
That's not it.
違いますよ！
Sorry for having asked you to do all that.
ごめんね　全部お願いしちゃって
いえ　すぐ終わりましたから
No problem, I finished quickly.
ありがとう　ねっ　転校しちゃうってホント？
Thanks. So, is it true
that you'll be transferring schools?
あっ　はい　3学期いっぱいです
Ah, yes, at the end of the year.
どこ？
Where to?
Kagoshima. Because of my parents.
鹿児島です　親の都合で
そうかー　寂しくなるなぁ
I see... it'll be lonely around here without you.
最近は部活で朝が早いので
今　この手紙は電車で書いています
"I'm actually writing this letter on the train because
practice has been starting really early lately. "
この前　髪を切りました
"I had my hair cut the other day. "
"It's so short you can even see my ears... "
耳が出るくらい短くしちゃったから
もし会っても
私って分からないかもしれませんね
"... so you probably wouldn't even recognize me
if you saw me. "
ただいまー
I'm back.
おかえり
Welcome home.
タカキくんも　きっと少しずつ
変わっていくのでしょうね
"I bet you're changing little
by little too, Takaki-kun. "
"Dear Takaki-kun... "
拝啓　寒い日が続きますがお元気ですか？
"Have you been doing well during these cold days?"
こちらは　もう何度か雪が降りました
"It's already snowed a number of times here. "
私はそのたびにものすごい重装備で
学校にツ通っています
"Every time it does, I wrap myself
in layers of clothes when I go to school. "
東京は雪はまだだよね
"It hasn't snowed in Tokyo yet, right?."
"Even though I moved away... "
引越してきてからも
ついクセで
東京のぶんの天気予報まで見てしまいます
"... I still look at Tokyo's
weather forecast out of habit. "
ハァ　ハァ
雨でも降らねえかなぁ
Wish it would rain one of these days...
でも居内でもキツイぜ
It wouldn't be any better indoors.
なぁ　栃木って行ったことあるか？
Say... have you guys ever been to Tochigi?
ハァ？どこ？
Huh? Where?
Tochigi.
栃木
Nope.
ない
どうやって行くのかな？
I wonder how you get there...
さぁ...新幹線とか？
No clue.
A bullet train or something?
遠いよな
It's a long way...
一年！
Freshmen!
ハイ！
Yes?!
Onto the final three laps! Fight! Fight!
ラスト三周！
ファイト！オーッ！
今度はタカキくんの転校が
決まったということ驚きました
"I was surprised to hear that you were
the one transferring schools this time. "
お互いに昔から転校には
慣れているわけですが
"We both got used to transferring schools
when we were little.. "
それにしても鹿児島だなんて
"But still... Kagoshima.
That's kind of far away, isn't it?"
％今度はちょっと遠いよね
いざという時に
"It's no longer a distance where I can just
jump on a train and see you whenever I want... "
電車に乗って会いに行けるような
距離ではなくなってしまうのは
"So... I guess... that makes me feel a little lonely. "
やっぱり...
少し...
ちょっと寂しいです
どうか　どうか
タカキくんが元気でいますように
"Please be well, Takaki-kun. "
前略　タカキくんへ
"Dear Takaki-kun... "
3月4日の約束　とても嬉しいです
"I'm so happy we'll see each other on March 4th. "
会うのは　もう一年ぶりですね
"It'll be just about a year
since we last met, won't it?"
"For some reason, I feel kind of nervous. "
なんだか緊張してしまいます
うちの近くに大きな桜の樹があって
"There's a really large cherry tree close to
my house, so I bet that in the spring... "
春には　そこでもたぶん
花びらが秒速5センチで地上に降っています
"... the petals will fall
at five centimeters per second. "
タカキくんと一緒に
"I'm really hoping the spring
will come with you that day, Takaki-kun. "
春もやってきてくれればいいのにって思います
Wanna stop somewhere on the way home?
Well... it's raining out.
The forecast said it's supposed
to turn to snow by tonight.
予報では夕方から雪になるって
Really? I thought it felt cold.
え～っ　寒いと思ったよ
もう3月なのにな
And we're already in March...
風邪引きそうだよね
Yeah, it feels like I'm gonna catch a cold.
ねっ　あったかいもの
飲んでこうよ　下北で降りてさ
We can get off at Shimokita.
そうだな
Yeah.
遠野
Tohno, let's get to practice.
部活行こうぜ
あぁ
Right...
あのさ　俺
今日ちょっと部活ダメなんだ
About that... I don't think I can make it today.
引越しの準備か？
Getting ready to move?
Something like that.
そんなトコ　悪いな
Sorry.
私の駅まで来てくれるのはとても
助かるのですけれど
"I'm glad you're coming all the way out
to the station closest to me... "
遠いので
どうか気をつけてきて下さい
"... but it's a long trip, so please be careful. "
約束の夜7時に駅の待合室で待っています
"I'll be waiting for you in the station's
waiting room at 7:00 that night. "
アカリとの約束の当日は昼すぎから雪になった
On the day Akari and I were to meet,
the rain turned to snow in the afternoon.
あっ　ねえタカキくん！
Hey, Takaki-kun.
ねこ！チョビだ！
It's that cat, Chobi.
こいつ　いつもここにいるね
He's always lying here.
でも今日は１人みたい
But it looks like he's all by himself today.
ミミは　どうしたの？
１人じゃ寂しいよねぇ
What happened to your friend Mimi?
It must be lonely all by yourself, huh?
ハァ　ハァ
あの本　どう？
How's that book so far?
なかなか
昨日一晩で40億年分読んじゃった！
I really like it.
Last night I read four billion years' worth of evolution.
どのあたり？
Where are you at now?
アノマロカリスが出てくるあたり
Just about when the Anomalocaris start showing up.
カンブリア紀！
The Cambrian era!
I really like the Hallucigenia. They look like this!
私　ハルキゲニアが好きだな　こんなの
まあ　似てるかも
Yeah, something like that...
タカキくんは何のファン？
Which one do you like, Takaki-kun?
オパビニアかな
The Opabinia, maybe?
あー　眼が5つあるヒトだよね！
The five-eyed one, right?
僕とアカリは
精神的にどこかよく似ていたと思う
I think Akari and I were a lot alike somehow.
Exactly one year after I transferred to Tokyo...
僕が東京に転校してきた１年後にー
A new friend just transferred to our school.
This is Tohno Takaki-kun.
アカリが同じクラスに転校してきた
...Akari transferred into my class.
Starting today, Shinohara Akari-san
will be joining our class.
まだ体が小さく病気がちだった僕らは
Because our bodies were still small,
frail, and prone to illness...
...the two of us preferred the library
over playing on the sportsfield.
グランドよりは図書館が好きで
だから僕たちはごく自然に仲良くなり
Naturally, we became friends...
そのせいでクラスメイトから
からかわれることもあったけれど
...and because of that, there were times when
our classmates would tease us. But...
Those two are always together.
でもー
Ooh! There he is!
お互いがいれば不思議にそういうことは
あまり怖くはなかった
As long as we were both together,
strangely, things like that didn't scare us.
Aw, what a nice guy!
Wow!
僕たちは　いずれ同じ中学に通い
And yet, for some reason, I thought we'd
end up going to the same middle school...
...and stay together, just as we were...
この先もずっと一緒にだと
どうしてだとう　そう思っていた
...from that point on.
Shinjuku, Shinjuku, last stop. For passengers which...
新宿　新宿　終点です
お振りのお客様は...
ＪＲ線　京王線
地下鉄はお乗り換えです...
...JR Line, Heiou Line, subway...
新宿駅に1人で来たのは初めてで
It was the first time I'd gone
to Shinjuku Station alone...
これから乗る路線も僕にはすべて初めてだった
...and all the lines I would soon be riding
would also be firsts for me.
ハァ...
ドキドキしていた
My heart was pounding.
これから　僕は　アカリに会うんだ
I was going to see Akari again.
この前の子　どうだった？
How did it go with that guy?
誰？
Who?
ほら　西商の！
You know, that Nisshou boy.
え～？趣味悪くない？
Are you kidding? His tastes were a little gross...
We will be arriving at Musashi-Urawa shortly.
Again, this is Musashi-Urawa.
At our next stop, Musashi-Urawa,
in order to connect with the express train...
...快速列車
待ち合わせのためこの列車は４分ほど停車します
In order to connect with the express train,
this train will be stopping for 4 minutes.
Those passengers who wish to quickly reach Yonohonmachi
and Oomiya please board...
与野本町
大宮までお急ぎの方は向かいの...
あの...篠原と申しますけど
Um... this is Shinohara.
あの　タカキくんいらっしゃいますか？
Umm, is Takaki-kun there?
アカリちゃんよ
It's Akari-chan.
え...転校？
Huh? You're transferring schools?
西中はどうすんだ？せっかく受かったのに
What about Nishi Middle School?
You went through all that trouble to get accepted.
栃木の公立に手続きするって...
They said they'd handle the paperwork of transferring
me to the public school in Tochigi...
ごめんね
I'm sorry...
いや...アカリが謝ることないけで
No... there's no reason to apologize.
葛飾の叔母さんちから　通いたいって言ったんだけど
I told them I still wanted to go
from my aunt's house in Katsushika, but...
...they said I couldn't until I was older.
もっと大きくなってからじゃないとダメだって...
わかった
I understand... you don't have to say anything else.
もういいよ
もういい
That's enough.
ごめん...
I'm sorry...
耳が痛くなるくらい　押しあてた受話器ごしに
Through the receiver painfully pressed
against my ear...
アカリが傷つくのが手にとるように分かった　でも...
...Akari's own pain was palpable.
But... there was nothing I could do.
どうしようもなかった
That was pretty good, huh?
Yeah. See you later!
乗り換えのターミナル駅は帰宅を
始めた人々で混み合っていて
The terminal I transferred at
was crowded with people heading home...
誰の靴も雪の水を吸ってぐっしょり濡れていて
...and everyone's shoes were soaked from the snow.
空気はー
The frigid air was saturated with the classic smell
of a snowy city day.
雪の日の都市　独特の匂いに満ちて冷たかった
お客様にお知らせいたします
All passengers, your attention please.
宇都宮線　小山　宇都宮方面行き列車は
Due to the snowy weather conditions, the Utsunomiya Line
outbound trains traveling to Oomiya and Utsunomiya...
ただいま雪のため　到着が８分ほど遅れております
...will be experiencing an 8 minute delay in arrival.
お急ぎのところお客様には
大変ご迷惑おかけいたしますが
We apologize for any inconvenience in your busy day.
その瞬間まで　僕は電車が遅れるなんていう可能性を
Until that moment, I hadn't even considered
the possibility of one of my trains being late.
考えもしなかった
不安が急に大きくなった
My creeping anxiety suddenly became much greater.
ただいまこの電車は雪のため
１０分ほど遅れて運行しております
This train is currently running 10 minutes late
due to the snowy weather conditions.
お急ぎのところ列車遅れておりますこと　お詫びいたします
We apologize for any inconvenience in your busy day.
大宮駅を過ぎてしばらくすると
After we had passed a little beyond Oomiya Station...
...almost all the passing buildings
suddenly vanished from view.
風景からはあっという間に建物が少なくなった
Next stop is Kuki. Kuki.
次は久喜　久喜
到着が大変遅れましたこと
お詫び申し上げます
We apologize for our terribly late arrival.
東武伊勢崎線にお乗り換えの方は
５番出口におまわり下さい
Those passengers transferring to the Tobu Isesaki Line,
please make your way around to Exit #5.
後続列車が遅れているため
Due to the next train's delay, this train will be stopping
at this station for the next 10 minutes.
この列車は到駅にて１０分ほど停車します
お急ぎのところ大変ご迷惑おかけいたしますが
We apologize for any inconvenience in your busy day,
and appreciate your understanding.
今しばらくお待ち下さいますよう
お願いいたします
すみません
Sorry about that.
後続列車が遅れているため
Due to the next train's delay, this train will be stopping
at this station for the next 10 minutes.
この列車は到駅にて１０分ほど停車します
We apologize for any inconvenience in your busy day, and...
お急ぎのところ大変ご迷惑を
おかけいたしますが...
野木　野木
This is Nogi. Nogi.
お客様にお断りとお詫び申し上げます
To all passengers, we express our deepest apologies.
Due to the continuing delay of the following train, this train will
be stopping at this station for an extended period of time.
後続列車遅延のため
この列車は当駅でしばらくの間停車します
お急ぎのところ大変ご迷惑...
We apologize for any inconvenience in your busy day,
and appreciate your understanding.
駅と駅との間は信じられないくらい
離れていて
電車は一駅ごとに
信じられないくらい長い間 停車した
...and the train would stop for an unbelievably
long amount of time at each station.
Kurihashi > Koga > Nogi > Mamada > Oyama
Omoigawa > Tochigi > Ohirashita > Iwafune > Sano
窓の外の見たこともないような雪に荒野も
The wilderness on the other side of the
window seemed like nothing I'd ever experienced before.
じわじわと流れていく時間も
痛いような空腹も
The slowly ticking time...
...and my pangs of hunger...
僕をますます心細くさせていった
...continued to dampen my spirits.
約束の時間を過ぎて
The time we had planned to meet had passed...
今頃アカリは
きっと不安になり始めていると思う
...so I had the feeling that Akari was beginning to worry.
あの日...あの電話の日ー
On that day...
...the day she called...
僕よりもずっと大きな不安を
抱えているはずのアカリに対して
...Akari must've been so much more jittery and upset than me,
yet I couldn't find the words to console her.
優しい言葉をかけることのできなかった自分が
ひどく　恥ずかしかった
I felt so ashamed of myself.
As we look back, we thank our teachers
for all they've done.
あおげば尊し...
じゃあ
今日でショナラだね
Then I guess after today... this is goodbye.
Any summer vacation plans?
アカリからの最初の手紙が
届いたのはそれから半年後
I received the first letter from Akari
half a year later...
中１の夏だった
...during the summer of my first year of middle school.
I remember every last word of it.
彼女からの文面はすべて覚えた
Over the two weeks before the day we were to meet...
約束の今日まで２週間かけて
...I spent my time writing a letter I would give her.
僕はアカリに渡すための手紙を書いた
It was filled with all the things I had to tell her.
アカリに伝えなければいけないこと
聞いて欲しいことが
All the things I wanted her to hear.
There were so many.
本当に　僕にはたくさんあった
大変お待たせいたしました
まもなく宇都宮行き発車いたします
We apologize terribly for the wait.
This train will shortly begin
its departure towards Utsunomiya.
This is Oyama. Oyama.
小山　小山
For those passengers changing over to the
Tohoku Bullet Train, please transfer here.
東北新幹線ご利用の方は
お乗り換えです
Those passengers transferring to the down-train,
the Tohoku Bullet Train towards Morioka, please transfer to Line 1.
東北新幹線下り盛岡方面
お乗り換えの方は１番線
Those passengers transferring to the up-train
towards Tokyo, please transfer to Line 5.
上り東京方面お乗り換えの方は
５番線へおまわり下さい
Those passengers transferring to the Mito Line-
お客様にお知らせいたします
Due to snowy weather conditions, the
Ryomo Line is currently experiencing a serious delay.
ただいま両毛線は雪のため
大幅な遅れをもって運転しております
お客様には大変ご迷惑をおかけいたしております
We apologize for the terrible inconvenience.
列車到着まで今しばらくお待ち下さい
We ask that you please be patient and wait
a little longer until the train arrives.
The next up-train headed for-
とにかく
アカリの待つ駅に向かうしかなかった
...I had no choice but to keep going towards
the station where Akari was waiting.
This is the up-train, Line 8, towards Takasaki,
passing Ashikaga and Maebashi on the way.
８番線
足利.前橋方面高崎行き上り電車が参ります
白線の内側に下がって...
Please stand behind the white line-
All passengers, your attention please.
お客様にご案内いたします
ただいま降雪によるダイヤの乱れのため
少々停車いたします
Due to the disrupted schedule from the heavy snowfall
this train will be making a temporary stop.
お急ぎのところ大変　恐縮ですが
We apologize terribly for this inconvenience in your busy day...
現在のところ復旧の目処は
立っておりません
...but presently, we are unable to resume normal service.
繰り返します
I repeat...
ただいま降雪によるダイヤの乱れのため
少々停車いたします
お急ぎのところ大変　恐縮ですが
現在のところ復旧の目処は
立っておりません
"Dear Takaki-kun... "
タカキくん　お元気ですか？
"How are you?"
"I'm actually writing this letter on the train because
practice has been starting really early lately. "
部活で朝が早いので
この手紙は電車で書いています
Every time I tried to picture Akari from her letters...
手紙から想像するアカリはなぜか
いつも１人だった
...she was always alone for some reason.
In the end, the train remained stopped
in the barren wilderness for two hours.
電車はそれから結局ー
２時間も何もない荒野に停まり続けた
Each minute felt like an eternity.
たった１分がものすごく長く感じられ
With clear malice towards me...
時間は　はっきりとした悪意をもって
...time continued to drift slowly forwards around me.
僕は上をゆっくりと流れていった
I clenched my teeth tightly together...
僕は　きつく歯をくいしばり
ただとにかく
泣かないように耐えているしかなかった
...and could do nothing but endure the pain
and hold back my tears.
Akari...
アカリ...
Please tell me...
どうか...もう...
...you've already...
家に...
...returned home.
帰っていてくれればいいのに...
Line 3 towards Takasaki, passing Ashikaga
and Maebashi on the way has just arrived.
３番線 足利.前橋方面高崎行き列車
到着いたします
Due to the snowy weather conditions, this train
will be making a temporary stop.
この電車は雪にためしばらく停車します
ハァッ
ウッ...
Akari...
アカリ
おいしい
It tastes good.
そう？普通のほうじ茶だよ
Really?
It's just hot roasted tea.
ほうじ茶？初めて飲んだ
Roasted tea?
This is my first time having it...
You're kidding. I'm sure you've had it before.
ウソ　ぜったい　飲んだことあるよ！
そうかな？
You think?
そうだよ！
You must have.
それからこれ...
私が作ったから味の保証はないんだけど
And... since I made this, I can't really guarantee
how good it'll taste, but...
よかったら食べて
If you'd like, please have some.
ありがとう
Thanks!
I was really hungry.
お腹すいてたんだ　すごく
How is it?
どうかな？
今まで食べたものの中で一番おいしい
It's the most delicious rice ball I've ever had.
大袈裟だなぁ
You're exaggerating!
ホントだよ
It really is!
It's probably just because you're hungry.
きっとお腹がすいてたからよ
すうかな
You think so?
It must be.
そうよ予5占
私も食べよっと
I think I'll have a bite, too.
So... you're moving soon, right?
引越し　もうすぐだよね
Yeah. Next week.
うん　来週
Kagoshima, huh?
鹿児島かぁ
遠いんだ
It's pretty far away.
うん
Yeah...
栃木も遠かったけどね
Though this trip to Tochigi was pretty far, too.
ふふ　帰れなくなっちゃったもんね
You can't even go home today now, after all.
そろそろ閉めますよ もう電車もないですし
We'll be closing soon.
There aren't any more trains coming or going.
ハイ
Yes, sir.
ほんな雪ですから　お気をつけて
Be careful on your way home in this snow.
ハイ！
Yes, sir.
Can you see the tree way out there?
見える？あの樹
手紙の樹？
Is that the tree from your letters?
Yeah. It's a cherry tree.
うん　桜の樹
ねえ
So...
まるで...雪みたいじゃない？
...don't you think it looks a little like snow?
そうだね
It sure does.
その瞬間ー
In that moment...
永遠とか心とか魂とかいうものが
どこにあるのか
...I felt like I knew where eternity,
our hearts and ours souls all lay.
分かった気がした
I felt as though we had shared
all the experiences of my 13 years.
13年間　生きてきたことの全てを
分かちあえたように僕は思い
それから　次の瞬間ー
And then... in the next moment...
たまらなく...
...I was suddenly filled
with an insufferable sadness.
悲しくなった
Akari's warmth... and her soul...
アカリのその温もりを　その魂を
How could I take them in,
and where could I bring them?
どのように扱えばいいのか
どこに持っていけばいいのか
I felt that sad because I didn't have those answers.
それが僕には分からなかったからだ
I clearly knew that from that point on,
we wouldn't be together forever.
僕たちはこの先も
ずっと一緒にいることはできないと
はっきりと分かった
The overwhelming weight of our lives to come...
僕たちの前には　いまだ巨大すぎる人生が
...and the uncertainty of time hung over us.
茫漠とした時間がどうしようもなく
横たわっていた
But... the creeping anxiety that had taken hold of me...
でもー
僕を捉えたその不安は
やがてゆるやかに溶けていき
...would soon gradually melt away.
あとにはアカリの
柔らかな唇だけが残っていた
And all that remained would be
the feeling of Akari's soft lips.
We spent that night in a shack
by the side of a field.
その夜ー
僕たちは畑の脇にあった
小さな納屋で過ごした
Wrapping ourselves in an old blanket,
we talked on and on...
古い毛布にくるまり
長い時間話し続けて
いつの間にか眠っていた
...until finally, we had fallen asleep, side by side.
朝　動き始めた電車に乗って
The next morning, as I boarded the train
that had started its run again...
僕はアカリと別れた
...I parted with Akari..
あの...
Umm... Takaki-kun...
タカキくん...
Yeah?
ん...？
タカキくんは...
Takaki-kun...
きっとこの先も大丈夫だと思う
ぜったい！
...I'm sure you'll be okay from now on.
I just know it!
ありがとう
Thank you.
アカリも元気で！
Akari, you be well, too!
手紙書くよ！電話も！
I'll write you!
I'll call, too!
アカリへの手紙をなくしてしまったことを
I never told Akari that I'd lost the letter
I wanted to give her.
僕はアカリに言わなかった
Because I felt that my world
had completely changed after that kiss.
あのキスの前と後とでは
世界の何もかもが
変わってしまったような気がしたからだ
彼女を守れるだけの力が
欲しいと強く思った
All I wanted was the strength to protect her.
With that thought in my mind, I continued to gaze out
over the landscape beyond the window... forever.
それだけを考えながら僕はいつまでも
窓の外の景色を見続けていた
Kanae, are you going to go after school, too?
カナエ　放課後も行くの？
うん　お姉ちゃんは平気？
Yeah, are you okay with that, Onee-chan?
いいよ　でも勉強もちゃんとやんなさいよ
Fine by me. But be sure to get to your studies, too.
Yeah.
はーい
ふう...よし
Okay!
おはよう
Morning.
Good morning, Tohno-kun.
おはよう　遠野くん　今朝も早いね
You're really early this morning, huh?
You too, Sumida. You went to the beach again, right?
澄田も　海　行ってきたんだろ？
Yeah.
頑張るんだね
You're practicing hard.
I wouldn't say that...
そんなにでも...へへへ
See you later, Tohno-kun.
またね！遠野くん
Later.
Got it? It's time to begin making your choices.
いいかぁ？　そろそろ決める時期だぞ
Be sure to turn it in by Monday, okay?
月曜までに提出だからな
And remember to talk it over with your parents before.
ご家族とよく相談して書いてくるように
Looks like Sasaki-san's gonna be going to a college in Tokyo.
佐々木さん　東京の大学行くみたいよ
No surprise there. I was thinking of maybe
going to a 2-year college in Kumamoto.
さすが 私の熊本の短大かな～
What about you, Kanae?
カナエは？
Huh? Umm...
え？うーん...
Will you get a job?
就職だっけ？
うーん...
Umm...
You really haven't thought about it at all, huh?
あんたホンと何も考えてないよね
The only thing on your mind is Tohno-kun, right?
遠野くんのことだけね
He definitely left his girlfriend in Tokyo, I'm telling you.
あいつゼッタイ　東京に彼女いるよ
そんなぁ！
No way!
うっふふふ
Still not going well for you?
まだ上手くいかない？
Yeah... what's gotten into me?
うん　どうしちゃったのかな...
It's better if you don't think about it too much.
You'll be able to surf again in no time, I promise.
あんまり　悩まない方がいいよ
そのうちまた乗れるわよ
お姉ちゃんは気楽でいいわよ
It must be nice taking things so easy, Onee-chan.
What are you in such a rush for?
なに　焦ってんのよ
このままじゃ卒業まで言えないじゃない
At this rate, I won't be able to say it before graduation...
Thanks, Onee-chan.
ありがと　お姉ちゃん
I can take you home, too...
送ってくわよ
Don't worry about it. I'll take my bike home.
ううん　カブで帰る！
あっ　澄田　今帰り？
Sumida, you're on your way home?
Yeah.
うん　遠野くんも？
You too, Tohno-kun?
Yeah.
ああ...
Wanna go home together?
一緒に帰らない？
If I had a tail like a dog's...
もし私に犬みたいな尻尾があったら
もっと嬉しさを隠しきれずに
ぶんぶんと振ってしまったと思う
...I'm sure it'd be wagging back and forth right now,
since I'd be unable to hide my happiness.
I was sort of relieved and thought to myself,
"Thank goodness I'm not really a dog... "
ああ　私は犬じゃなくて良かったな～
なんてホッとしながら思って
そういうことに我ながらバカだなぁと呆れて
...and I was surprised at how foolish I was
for thinking what I did earlier.
But even still, the trip home with Tohno-kun was bliss.
それでも
遠野くんとの帰り道は幸せだった
最初から遠野くんは他の男の子たちとは
どこか少し違っていた
Right from the start, Tohno-kun seemed
a little different from the other boys.
遠野貴樹です
I'm Tohno Takaki.
I'm sorta used to transferring schools
because of my parents' jobs...
親の仕事で転校には慣れていますが
この島にはまだ慣れていません
...but I'm not too used to this island yet.
It's nice to meet you all.
よろしくお願いします
I fell in love at first sight on that day in the second year of middle
school, and wanted to go to the same high school as him...
中2のその日のうちに好きになって
彼と同じ高校に行きたくて
...so I studied really hard, was somehow accepted...
ものすごく勉強をがんばって
なんてか合格して
...and every single time I saw him,
fell more and more in love with him.
それでもまだ遠野くんの姿を見るたびに
もっと好きになっていってしまって
But it's so scary, and everyday is painful.
それが怖くて　毎日が苦しくて
Yet every time I see him, I'm filled with such happiness...
でも会えるたびに幸せで
...that I'm at a loss for what to do.
自分でもどうしようもなかった
Tohno-kun, there you go buying the same one again.
遠野くん　また　同じの
ふふ　これウマいんだよ
It's really good.
Sumida, you always think your decisions
through seriously, don't you?
澄田は　なんかいつも真剣だよね
ものすごく
うん！
Yeah.
I'll be outside.
先行ってるよ
Yeah.
うん...
これ下さい
Just this, please.
That'll be 90 yen.
90円ね
Here you go.
ハイ
Thanks as always.
いつも　ありがとね
ハッ！
お帰り　何買ったの？
Welcome back.
What'd you buy?
うん　迷ったんだけど...
Well, it was hard to pick, but I went with this.
Sometimes, Tohno-kun would be writing a text message...
遠野くんは時々
誰かにメールを打っていて
そのたびに私は　それが
私あてのメールだったらいいのにって
...and every time he did, I would always wish...
...that the text message he was writing...
どうしても　いつも　思ってしまう
...would be addressed to me.
ワン！
ワンワン！ワン！
Kabu, I'm home!
カブ！ただいまー！
Kabu, Kabu!
カブカブ　帰ってきたよ！
I'm back.
ワフッ
町役場からお知らせします
次回の当番スタンドは坂井の農協給油...
This is a message from your town hall.
The next normal open gasoline stand will be at the
Sakai Agricultural Cooperative Gas Station.
Sumida Kanae-san from Class 3-1...
3年1組の澄田花苗さん
伊藤先生がお呼びです
生徒指導室まで来て下さい
...Itou-sensei is calling for you.
Please report to the Guidance Counselor's office.
遠野の彼女じゃん
That's your girlfriend, Tohno.
She's not my girlfriend.
彼女とかじゃないよ
You're the only one in the grade who hasn't filled one out.
学年で出してないのは澄田だけだぞ
I'm sorry.
すみません...
Look, this isn't something someone in my position
should be saying...
あのなぁ　こう言っちゃ何だが
そんなに悩むようなことじゃないんだよ
...but this isn't really something
you have to wrack your brain over.
Has Sumida-sensei said anything?
澄田先生は何て言ってるんだ？
No...
いえ...
ふうっ...
If you really can't decide, then how about
a 2-year college within the prefecture?
どうしても決められないなら
県内の短大とかはどうなんだ？
でも...
But...
Onee-chan has nothing to do with it...
お姉ちゃんは関係ないのに...
だって...
After all...
お姉ちゃんにねだって
はじめたサーフィンも
...surfing, even after I pestered my sister
so much to teach me...
...and the most important guy who takes up all of my thoughts...
一番大切だと思う　あの人のことも
私はまだ　全然...
...are two things I'm still no good at.
いつもありがとね
Thanks as always.
Not at all. See you next time.
いえ　それじゃあまた
Whenever I go to where Tohno-kun is...
遠野くんがいる場所にくると
...deep down, my heart... it clenches up... just a little.
胸の奥が...少し苦しくなる
遠野くん！
Tohno-kun.
澄田?どうしたの　よく分かったね
Sumida, what's up? I'm surprised you found me way out here.
へへへ　遠野くんの単車があったから
来ちゃった　いい？
I saw your bike, so I decided to come on by.
That okay?
Ah, I see. I'm glad to see you.
うん　そっか　嬉しいよ
今日は単車置き場で会えなかったからさ
We didn't run into each other at the bike shed today.
私も！
I'm glad, too.
彼は優しい
He's really kind.
So kind that sometimes it feels like I'm going to cry.
時々　泣いてしまいそうになる
Hey, are you going to test to get into college?
ねえ　遠野くんは受験？
Yeah. I'm going to take a few for some universities in Tokyo.
うん　東京の大学受ける
Tokyo... I see.
東京...そっか　そうだと思ったんだ
I thought that might be the case.
Why do you say that?
どうして？
You seem like you want to go far away from here, for some reason...
遠くに行きたそうだもの
なんとなく
What about you, Sumida?
澄田は？
う～ん...
I don't even really know what's going to happen tomorrow.
私　明日のこともよく分からないのよね
Everyone's the same.
だぶん　誰だってそうだよ
No way! You too, Tohno-kun?
ワン！遠野くんも？
Of course.
もちろん
You don't look like you have anything to worry about.
ぜんぜん　迷いなんてないみたいに見える
まさか　迷ってばかりなんだ　俺
Oh, stop that. I'm filled with nothing but worries.
I'm doing all that I can just to keep up.
I have no breathing room.
出来ることをなんとかやってるだけ
余裕ないんだ
Really?
そっか...
I see...
そうなんだ
A plane?
飛行機？
Yeah.
Wow...
..すごい
They say it travels at five kilometers per hour.
時速5キロなんだって
えっ？
It's going to the Minamitane launch facility.
南種子の打ち上げ場まで
ああ...
Looks like there'll be a launch this year.
First time in a while.
今年は久しぶりに打ち上げるんだよね
ああ　太陽系のずっと奥まで
行くんだって
Yeah. It's supposed to go to the far reaches
of the solar system.
No matter how many years it takes...
何年もかけて
Hey... you should really talk to Kanae
about her plans for the future.
あんた　カナエの進路
ちゃんと相談に乗ってやんなさいよ
You know how absent-minded she can be.
ぼんやりした子なんだから
She'll be fine. It's not like she's a child anymore.
大丈夫よ　あの子も
もう子供じゃないんだし
I remember when I used to be just like that, a long time ago...
私も昔は　ああだったなぁ...
Hear that, Kabu? Tohno-kun apparently doesn't
know what tomorrow will bring, either.
ねえ　カブ　遠野くんも分からないんだって
We're both the same. Tohno-kun and me.
一緒なんだ...遠野くんも
It must really be...
それは本当に...
想像を絶するくらい　孤独な旅であるはずだ
...a lonelier journey than anyone could imagine.
To just press forward through
the true pitch darkness...
本当の暗閣の中をただひたむきに
Barely encountering even a single hydrogen atom...
1つの水素原子にさえ滅多に出会うことなく
Wholeheartedly believing
you'll come closer to discovering...
ただただ　深淵にあるはずと信じる
世界の秘密に近づきたいー心で
...the secrets of the universe
within the unfathomable abyss of space.
I wonder how far we should go...
僕たちは　そうやって
どこまで行くのだろう
How far CAN we go?
どこまで行けるのだろう
I wonder when I got in the habit of
writing messages to nobody?
出すあてのないメールを打つクセがついたのは
いつからだろう
Kanae, have you decided what you'll be doing in the future?
カナエ　あんた　進路決めたの？
Nope. Like I thought, I'm still not sure...
ううん　やっぱりまだ分かんないけど　でもいいの決めたの！
But it's all right! I decided that
I'll just take things on one at a time.
1つずつ出来ることからやるの行ってくる！
Off I go!
Since that day, a number of typhoons
have passed through...
あの日から　いくつかの台風が通りすぎ
...and the island's
become a little cooler each time.
そのたびに島は少しずつす
ずしくなっていった
The wind blowing through the sugarcane
has taken on a slight chill...
サトウキビを揺らす風が
かすかに冷気を孕み
...and the sky seems a little higher.
空がほんの少し高くなり
The edges of the clouds have become gentler...
雲の輪郭が優しくなって
カブに乗る同級生たちが
薄いシャンパーを羽織るようになった
...and my classmates have begun wearing light jackets
when riding their bikes with the change in the weather.
By the time I managed to ride the waves again,
six long months had passed.
私が半年ぶりに波の上に立てたのは
また夏がかろうじてのるそんな10月の半ばだった
Even though it was the middle of October, it felt
like a little bit of summer had been left behind.
本日夕方からの天候は晴れ
最大風速は8mの予報となっています
The weather forecast for tonight shows a clear evening
with winds up to eight meters per second.
佐々木さん　山田から告白されたらしいよ
So I heard that Yamada confessed to Sasaki-san.
No surprise there.
さすがだなー
Huh? Kanae, you seem awfully happy today.
あれ？カナエ　なんか今日嬉しそうね
Something good happen between you and Tohno-kun?
遠野くんとなんかあったの？
No way!
ワン！
Today, I'm finally going to confess to Tohno-kun, too.
私だって今日こそ...
遠野くんに告白するんだ
If I don't tell him today, on the day
I finally rode the waves again...
波に乗れた今日言わなければ
...I'm sure I won't ever be able to.
この先の　きっと...ずっと言えない
澄田
Sumida.
To-
と...
Tohno-kun.
遠野くん...
On your way home?
今帰り？
Yeah.
そっか
I see.
Then, let's go home together.
じゃあ　一緒に帰ろうよ
Huh, Sumida? Decided already today?
あれ　澄田　今日はもう決まり？
Yeah.
どうしたの？
What's the matter?
...しくしないで
...to me...
え？
No... I'm sorry. It's nothing.
ごめん...何でもないの
調子悪い？
Is your bike acting up?
Yeah... that's kind of weird.
うん　ヘンだなぁ
Is it broken?
ダメ？
Yeah... I think the spark plug's dead.
うん...プラグの寿命なんじゃないのかなこれお下がり？
Was this a hand-me-down?
うん　お姉ちゃんの
Yeah. It was Onee-chan's.
加速で息継ぎしてなかった？
Did it stall when you tried accelerating?
してたかも
It might have, actually...
Let's leave it here for today.
今日はここに置かせてもらって
後で家の人に取りにきてもらいなよ
You can have someone from your house pick it up later.
今日は歩こう
Let's walk back today.
Huh? I'll walk by myself!
えっ　私一人で歩くよ!
遠野くんは先帰って
You go on ahead.
We're this far out, and your place is nearby, so...
ここまできれば近いから
それにちょっと...歩きたいんだ
And... I kind of want to walk today.
遠野くん...
Tohno-kun, please...
お願い...
どうしたの！？
What's wrong?
I'm sorry...
ごめん　なんでもないの
It's nothing.
I'm so sorry...
ごめんね...
Sumida...
澄田...
I'm begging you... please...
お願いだから...もう...
私に...
...don't be so nice to me!
やさしくしないで....！
As we humans desperately and recklessly
stretched our arms to the top of the sky...
必死に　ただ閣雲に空に手を伸ばして
あんなに大きなカタマリを打ち上げて
...and launched something
of that mass and size into the air...
...gazing off into the distance towards something
far beyond our wildest dreams...
気の遠くなるくらい　むこうにある何か見つめて
...I felt like I somewhat came to understand why
Tohno-kun was different from the other boys.
遠野くんが他の人と
違って見える理由が
少しだけ分かった気がした
And at the same time...
そして　同時に
...I clearly realized that Tohno-kun
wasn't really looking at me.
遠野くんは私を見てなんて
いないんだということに
私はハッキリと気づいた
Which is why, on that day,
I couldn't say a word to Tohno-kun.
だからその日　私の遠野くんに
何も言えなかった
Tohno-kun is really kind, but...
遠野くんは優しいけれど
He's so truly kind, but...
とても優しいけれど
でもー
But Tohno-kun was always looking far beyond me.
遠野くんはいつも
私のずっとむこう...
もっとずっと遠くの何かを見ている
Far beyond me, towards something in the distance.
I'm sure I wouldn't be able to give Tohno-kun
what he truly desires.
私が遠野くんに望むことは
きっと叶わない
But still... despite that...
それでも...
それでも私は遠野くんのことを
Tomorrow, the day after, and even beyond that...
きっと明日も明後日もその先も
...I know I'll still be helplessly in love with him.
やっぱりどうしようもなく好きなんだと思う
While thinking solely of Tohno-kun,
I cried myself to sleep.
遠野くんのことだけを想いながら
泣きながら　私は眼った
I strongly felt...
今　振り返れば
...that if I looked back now...
きっとあの人振り返ると強く感じた
...she would look back as well.
The last Chuo line train bound for Tokyo is now arriving.
中央.総武最終電車　東京行きが到着します
You should stay till New Year's.
お正月でいればいいのに
I know, but I have a million things to take care of.
うん...でも色々準備もあるから
I guess so.
そうだな　彼にもうまいもの作ってやれよ
Be sure to cook him good meals, you hear?
I will.
If there's ever a problem, don't hesitate to call us, Akari.
何かあったら電話するのよ　アカリ
I'll be fine.
大丈夫よ　来月には式で会うんだから
そんなに心配しないで
We'll see each other at the wedding next month,
so don't worry so much.
You'd better head home. It's cold.
寒いからもう戻りなよ
Last night, I dreamt of something from the distant past.
ゆうべ　昔の夢を見た
私も彼も　まだ子供だった
Back when he and I were both still children.
きっと　昨日見つけた手紙のせいだ
I'm sure it's because of that letter I found yesterday.
Mizuno-san.
水野さん
Ah, yes, sir?
あ　はい
Have time for that meeting?
ミーテイングいいかな？
Yes, sir.
はい
Through the act of living itself,
sadness piles up here and there.
ただ　生活をしているだけで
哀しみはそこここに積もる
Whether in the sheets hung to dry in the sun...
日に干したシーツにも
洗面所の歯ブラシにも
...the single toothbrush in your bathroom...
...or the history logs of your cell phone.
携帯電話の履歴にも
"Even now, I still love you... "
あなたのことは今でも好きですと
That's what the girl I'd been with for three years
said in that e-mail.
三年間付き合った女性はそうメールに書いていた
"But I'm sure that even if we had written
1,000 text messages back and forth... "
でも私たちはきっと
1000回もメールをやりとりして
多分　心は1センチくらいしか
近づけませんでした と
"... our hearts probably wouldn't have moved
even 1 centimeter closer. "
この数年間　とにかく前に進みたくて
Over these past few years, I've only wanted to move
forward and touch that which I couldn't reach...
届かないものに手を触れたくて
それが具体的に何を指すのかも
...though I've never been able to tangibly define what it was.
Not knowing where those obsessive thoughts
came from, I simply continued to work.
ほとんと脅迫的とも
言えるようなその想いが
どこから湧いてくるのかも分からずに
僕はただ働き続け
Then one day I realized that my heart was withering,
and in it there was nothing but pain.
気づけば日々弾力を失っていく心が
ひたすら辛かった
And then, one morning...
そしてある朝
...when I realized that I had completely lost my
earnest and acute feelings from long ago...
かつてあれほどまでに真剣で切実だった思いが
綺麗に失われてることに僕は気づき
...I knew I was at my limit...
もう限界だと知ったとき
...and quit my job.
会社を辞めた
Yesterday, I had a dream.
昨日　夢を見た
A dream of long ago.
ずっと昔の夢
Within the dream, the two of us were still thirteen...
その夢の中では　僕たちはまだ13歳で
...standing upon the vast field blanketed
in snow as far as the eye could see.
そこは　一面の雪に覆われた広い田園で
In the distance, the lights shimmering in
houses were set sparsely, far and wide.
人家の灯りは　ずっと遠くにまばらに見えるだけで
振り積もる新雪には
私たちの歩いてきた足跡しかなかった
All that was left upon the newly fallen snow
were our footprints.
Just like that...
そうやって
いつかまた
一緒に桜を見ることが出来ると
...we wished, without hesitation, that one day...
...the two of us would be able...
私も彼も　なんの迷いもなく
...to see the cherry blossoms together again.
そう　思っていた
いつでも捜しているよ　どっかに君の姿を
I'm always searching for you,
always searching for your figure.
向いのホーム　路地裏の窓
On the opposite platform,
or through window in the back alley.
こんなとこにいるはずもないのに
Even though I know you can't be there.
願いがもしもかなうなら　今すぐ君のもとへ
If my wish were to come true, I would be at your side.
できないことは　もう何もない
There would be nothing I couldn't do.
すべてかけてだきしめてみせるよ
I would risk everything to embrace you.
寂しさ紛らすだけなら　誰でもいいはずなのに
If only to avoid loneliness, anyone will do.
星が落ちそうな夜だから　自分をいつわれない
On this night when it seem stars will fall
from the sky, I cannot lie to myself.
One more time　季節よ　うつろわないで
One more time, don't fade away, seasons.
One more time　ふざけあった時間よ
One more time, I want that time
when we fooled around together.
いつでも捜しているよ　どっかに君の姿を
I'm always searching for you,
always searching for your figure.
交差点でも　夢の中でも
At the intersection, in my dreams.
こんなとこにいるはずもないのに
Even though I know you can't be there.
奇跡はもしも起こるなら　今すぐ君に見せたい
If miracles do happen, I want to show you right now
新しい朝　これからの僕
the new dawn, who I'll be from now on,
言えなかった「好き」という言葉も
and the words "I love you" that I never said.
夏の想い出がまわる
The memories of summer revolve around me
ふいに消えた鼓動
and your throbbing heartbeat that suddenly stopped.
いつでも捜しているよ　どっかに君の姿を
I'm always searching for you,
always searching for your figure.
In the city at dawn, in Sakuragi-cho.
明け方の街　桜木町で
こんなとこに来るはずもないのに
Even though I know you can't be there.
願いがもしもかなうなら　今すぐ君のもとへ
If my wish were to come true, I would be at your side.
できないことは　もう何もない
There would be nothing I couldn't do.
すべてかけてだきしめてみせるよ
I would risk everything to embrace you.
いつでも捜しているよ　どっかに君の破片を
I'm always searching for you, always
searching for even a fragment of you.
旅先の店　新聞の隅
At the shop I'm going to, in the corner of a newspaper.
こんなとこにあるはずもないのに
Even though I know you can't be there.
奇跡はもしも起こるなら　今すぐ君に見せたい
If miracles do happen, I want to show you right now
新しい朝　これからの僕
the new dawn, who I'll be from now on,
言えなかった「好き」という言葉も
and the words "I love you" that I never said.
いつでも捜してしまう　どっかに君の笑顔を
I always end up looking somewhere for your smile.
急行待ちの　踏切あたり
At the railroad crossing, waiting for the express to pass.
こんなとこにいるはずもないのに
Even though I know you can't be there.
命が繰り返すならば　何度も君のもとへ
If I could live life over again,
I would be at your side every time.
欲しいものなど　もう何もない
Because I would want nothing
君のほかに大切なものなど
more precious than you.
The End